Twelve years ago, I was in the street writing my name
قبل اثني عشر سنة، كنت في الشارع أكتب إسمي
to say, "I exist."
"لأقول، "أنا موجود.
Then I went to taking photos of people to paste them on the street
ثم انتقلت إلى التقاط صور للناس ولصقها في الشارع
to say, "They exist."
"لأقول، "هم موجودون.
From the suburbs of Paris to the wall of Israel and Palestine,
من ضواحي باريس إلى جدار إسرائيل وفلسطين
the rooftops of Kenya
وسطوح كينيا
to the favelas of Rio,
.وصولا إلى الأحياء الفقيرة في ريو
paper and glue -- as easy as that.
الورق والغراء -- بتلك السهولة.
I asked a question last year:
:طرحت سؤالاً في السنة الماضية
Can art change the world?
هل يستطيع الفن تغيير العالم؟
Well let me tell you,
حسنا دعوني أخبركم،
in terms of changing the world there has been a lot of competition this year,
كانت هناك الكثير من المنافسة هذه السنة من حيث تغيير العالم،
because the Arab Spring is still spreading,
لأن الربيع العربي ما زال ينتشر،
the Eurozone has collapsed ... what else?
وقد انهارت منطقة اليورو... وماذا أيضا؟
The Occupy movement found a voice,
حركة "احتلوا" وجدت لها صوتا،
and I still have to speak English constantly.
ولا يزال يتوجب علي أن أتحدث الإنكليزية باستمرار.
So there has been a lot of change.
وبالتالي فقد حصل الكثير من التغيير.
So when I had my TED wish last year,
السنة الماضية, عندما أطلقت أمنيتي عبر TED
I said, look, I'm going to switch my concept.
قلت أنني سأقوم بتغيير مفهومي.
You are going to take the photos.
أنتم سوف تلتقطون الصور.
You're going to send them to me.
وتقومون بإرسالها إلي.
I'm going to print them and send them back to you.
وسأقوم بطباعتها وإعادة إرسالها إليكم.
Then you're going to paste them where it makes sense
ثم تقومون بلصقها حيث تجدونه منطقيا
for you to place your own statement.
أن تضعوا تصريحكم الخاص.
This is Inside Out.
إنه مشروع "رأساً على عقب" .
One hundred thousand posters have been printed this year.
تمت طباعة 100,000 ملصق هذه السنة.
Those are the kind of posters, let me show you.
تلك هي أنواع الملصقات، دعوني أريكم إياها.
And we keep sending more every day.
ونحن نواصل إرسال المزيد كل يوم.
This is the size.
هذا هو الحجم.
Just a regular piece of paper with a little bit of ink on it.
مجرد قطعة ورق عادية عليها القليل من الحبر.
This one was from Haiti.
هذه كانت من هاييتي.
When I launched my wish last year,
حين أطلقت أمنيتي في السنة الماضية،
hundreds of people stood up and said they wanted to help us.
مئات الناس وقفوا وقالوا أنهم يريدون مساعدتنا.
But I say it has to be
ولكنني أقول أنه يجب أن تكون
under the conditions I've always worked:
وفق الشروط التي اشتغلت وفقا لها:
no credit, no logos, no sponsoring.
من دون شعارات أو رعاة أو كلمة شكر.
A week later, a handful of people were there ready to rock
وبعد أسبوع، مجموعة جيدة من الناس كانت مستعدة للعمل الجاد
and empower the people on the ground
وتمكن الناس على أرض الواقع
who wanted to change the world.
الذين يريدون تغيير العالم.
These are the people I want to talk about to you today.
هؤلاء هم الذين أريد أن أحدثكم عنهم اليوم.
Two weeks after my speech, in Tunisia,
بعد أسبوعين من خطابي، في تونس
hundreds of portraits were made.
تم إنتاج مئات الصور الشخصية
And they pasted [over] every single portrait of the dictator
و ألصقوا فوق كل صورة شخصية للديكتاتور
[with] their own photos.
صورهم الخاصة.
Boom! This is what happened.
بوم! وهذا ما حدث.
Slim and his friends went through the country
سليم وأصدقائه جالوا عبر البلاد
and pasted hundreds of photos everywhere
وألصقوا مئات الصور في كل مكان
to show the diversity in the country.
لإظهار التنوع في البلاد.
They really make Inside Out their own project.
وقد جعلوا بالفعل "رأساً على عقب" مشروعهم الخاص.
Actually, that photo was pasted in a police station,
وفي الواقع، هذه الصورة ألصقت في مركز للشرطة،
and what you see on the ground
وما ترونه على الأرض
are ID cards of all the photos of people being tracked by the police.
هي بطاقات تعريف صور كل الأشخاص الذين تتعقبهم الشرطة.
Russia. Chad wanted to fight against homophobia in Russia.
في روسيا, تشاد يريد محاربة كراهية المثليين .
He went with his friends in front of every Russian embassy in Europe
ذهب مع أصدقائه إلى أمام كل سفارة روسية في أوروبا
and stood there with the photos
ووقفوا هناك مع الصور
to say, "We have rights."
للقول، "لدينا حقوق".
They used Inside Out as a platform for protest.
لقد استخدموا"رأساً على عقب" كمنصة للاحتجاج.
Karachi, Pakistan.
كراتشي، باكستان.
Sharmeen is actually here.
شارمين موجودة هنا الآن.
She organized a TEDx action out there
قد نظمت مبادرة TEDx هناك
and made all the unseen faces of the city
وقد وضعت كل الوجوه غير المرئية للمدينة
on the walls in her town.
على جدران بلدتها.
And I want to thank her today.
وأريد أن أشكرها اليوم.
North Dakota. Standing Rock Nation,
داكوتا الشمالية. أمة الصخرة الواقفة
in this Turtle Island, [unclear name] from the Dakota Lakota tribe
في جزيرة السلاحف هذه، "ديجي تو بيرز" من قبيلة "داكوتا لاكوتا"
wanted to show that the Native Americans are still here.
أراد أن يظهر أن الأمريكيين الأصليين لا يزالون هناك.
The seventh generation are still fighting for their rights.
الجيل السابع لا يزال يكافح من أجل حقوقه.
He pasted up portraits all over his reservation.
وقد ألصق الصور الشخصية في جميع أنحاء محميته.
And he's here also today.
وهو موجود هنا اليوم .
Each time I get a wall in New York,
في كل مرة أحصل على جدار في نيويورك،
I use his photos to continue spreading the project.
أستخدم صوره للاستمرار في نشر المشروع.
Juarez: You've heard of the border --
خواريز: قد سمعتم بالحدود
one of the most dangerous borders in the world.
واحد من أكثر الحدود خطورة في العالم.
Monica has taken thousands of portraits with a group of photographers
التقطت مونيكا آلاف الصور مع مجموعة من المصورين
and covered the entire border.
وغطت كامل الحدود.
Do you know what it takes to do this?
أتعرفون ما يلزم للقيام بذلك؟
People, energy, make the glue, organize the team.
الناس والطاقة وصناعة الغراء وتنظيم الفريق.
It was amazing.
كان ذلك مدهشاً.
While in Iran at the same time
في إيران, في الوقت نفسه
Abololo -- of course a nickname --
أبولولو -- بالطبع هو اسم مستعار --
has pasted one single face of a woman
ألصق وجه امرأة واحدة
to show his resistance against the government.
لإظهار مقاومته للحكومة.
I don't have to explain to you what kind of risk he took for that action.
ليس علي أن أشرح لكم حجم المخاطرة التي واجهها وهو يقوم بذلك.
There are tons of school projects.
هناك أطنان من المشاريع المدرسية.
Twenty percent of the posters we are receiving comes from schools.
تأتي 20% من الملصقات التي نستقبلها من المدارس
Education is so essential.
التعليم أمر أساسي.
Kids just make photos in a class, the teacher receives them,
يقوم الأطفال فقط بإنتاج الصور في الفصل ويستلمها المدرس
they paste them on the school.
يلصقونها على المدرسة.
Here they even got the help of the firemen.
حتى أنهم حصلوا هنا على مساعدة رجال الإطفاء .
There should be even more schools doing this kind of project.
ينبغي أن تقوم المزيد من المدارس بهذا النوع من المشاريع.
Of course we wanted to go back to Israel and Palestine.
بالطبع, كنا نرغب في العودة إلى إسرائيل وفلسطين.
So we went there with a truck. This is a photobooth truck.
فذهبنا مع شاحنة. هذه شاحنة كشك صور.
You go on the back of that truck, it takes your photo,
تذهب إلى الجزء الخلفي للشاحنة، فتلتقط صورتك،
30 seconds later take it from the side, you're ready to rock.
بعد 30 ثانية خذها من الجانب، وها أنت جاهز للانطلاق.
Thousands of people use them
آلاف الناس استخدموها
and each of them signs up for a two-state peace solution
وكل منهم وقع على حل سلام بدولتين
and then walk in the street.
ومن ثم مشوا في الشارع.
This is march, the 450,000 march -- beginning of September.
هذه هي المسيرة ، مسيرة ال450,000 -- بداية سبتمبر/أيلول.
They were all holding their photo as a statement.
كانوا جميعا يحملون صورهم كتعبير.
On the other side, people were wrapping up streets, buildings.
على الجانب الآخر، كان الناس يغلفون الشوارع والمباني.
It's everywhere.
إنها في كل مكان.
Come on, don't tell me that people aren't ready for peace out there.
هيا، لا تقولوا لي أن الناس ليسوا على استعداد للسلام هناك.
These projects took thousands of actions in one year,
هذه المشاريع تطلبت آلاف المبادرات في سنة واحدة،
making hundreds of thousands of people participating,
لجعل مئات الآلاف من الناس تشارك،
creating millions of views.
لخلق ملايين المشاهدات.
This is the biggest global art participatory project that's going on.
إنه أكبر مشروع فني تشاركي عالمي يجري حاليا.
So back to the question, "Can art change the world?"
إذن بالعودة للسؤال، "أيمكن للفن أن يغير العالم؟"
Maybe not in one year. That's the beginning.
ربما ليس في سنة واحدة. تلك هي البداية.
But maybe we should change the question.
ولكن ربما ينبغي لنا أن نغير السؤال.
Can art change people's lives?
أيمكن للفن أن يغير حياة الناس؟
From what I've seen this year, yes.
من خلال ما رأيته هذه السنة، نعم.
And you know what? It's just the beginning.
وتعرفون ماذا؟ إنها مجرد البداية.
Let's turn the world inside out together.
دعونا نقلب العالم رأساً على عقب معا.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)